DAN KLEIN: So what's rationality?
We have this idea that we
want rational agents.
We want utilities.
We know we have to have preferences.
Are there kind of good preferences
and bad preferences?
Are there always utility functions?
It all gets down to what exactly we
mean when we say rationality.
So preferences are the starting point.
Agents have preferences, and we're going
to try to figure out under what
circumstances those preferences can be
boiled down to a utility function.
So we'd like some constraints
on these preferences before
we call them rational.
There's a wide variety of
preferences that are OK.
Maybe the agent wants to make money.
Maybe the agent wants to spend money.
Maybe the agent likes ice cream.
Maybe the agent hates ice cream.
These are all perfectly good
preferences, but there are certain
kinds of preference that just make
no sense, and so we need some
constraints.
Here's one constraint.
The axiom of transitivity.
This says if you prefer a to b,
and you prefer b to c, you
better prefer a to c.
Well, that seems reasonable.
Why should we have this?
Well, if an agent has preferences
which do not obey
this, it has some flaws.
Like you can make it give away all
of its money, or anything else.
Because if, for example, if I likes b
better than c and it's got c, you can
give it b in return for,
maybe a penny.
But if it likes a better, you can now
give it a in return for a penny.
Oh, but wait, it likes
c better than a.
So now you give it c, which is where
it started, in return for a penny.
So it's back where it started, except
now you have three of its pennies.
And you keep doing this until
it has no more money.
This seems like a defect in behavior.
And so we're going to say we require
this axiom in order to declare
preferences rational.
That seems pretty reasonable.
There are more of them.
These are the actions of rationality.
So what do these say?
Let's look at them.
Orderability says given two things, you
either have to like a better, or
you have to like b better, or
you have to be indifferent.
It's kind of hard to argue with that.
Transitivity, we just saw.
It says if a is better than b, and b
is better than c, then a should be
better than c.
We've already seen what can happen
when that goes wrong.
The other ones are a little more subtle,
but they're pretty plausible.
So here's continuity.
Continuity says if you like a better
than c, and b is somewhere in the
middle, then there has to be some
lottery between a and c for which you
are indifferent between
the lottery and b.
And essentially, this means
you can interpolate.
If b is in between a and c, then
it's equivalent to some lottery
between a and c.
Substitutability.
This says if you're indifferent
between a and b, then you're
indifferent whenever they're
plugged into lotteries.
That makes sense.
If they're exchangeable on
their own, they should be
exchangeable in a lottery.
Monotonicity, also pretty reasonable.
This says that if a is better than b,
and you have a lottery between a and
b, then you'd prefer
more a in the mix.
That seems to make sense.
So here's a bunch of axioms.
There's a theorem that says rational
preferences that they obey these
axioms can be described as maximization
of expected utility.
Basically, if you accept these axioms,
there's a theorem that says all of
your preferences can be described
with the utility function.
So if you obey these axioms, we give
you the stamp of rationality.
And that means that preferences that
violate this are irrational.
Preferences that meet this are rational,
but there's still a lot of
wiggle room.
Lots of different preferences
meet this.
Here's the theorem.
The theorem says given any preferences
satisfying the axioms of rationality,
there exists a real valued function u
that has the following properties.
If you prefer a to b, it
has a higher utility.
So this utility function captures
your ordinal preferences.
And here's the amazing part.
The utility of a lottery is the
expectation of the utilities of the
elements of the lottery.
This means that this utility function
not only captures your ordinal
preferences amongst prizes,
but it captures your
preferences between lotteries.
It's amazing.
It means your utilities are preserved
under expectation.
Now we're back to the maximum
expected utility principal.
The principal says choose the action
that maximizes your expected utility.
And this is now well defined, because
the theorem says that if our
preferences were actually rational in
the first place, there is some such
utility function.
Now, an agent can be rational, meaning
consistent with the MEU principle
without ever actually representing
a utility, or manipulating a
probability.
For example, you can have a look
up table for tic-tac-toe.
You can have a reflex vacuum cleaner
that in a given configuration, just
goes after the closest dirt, and
that turns out to be optimal.
But still, you want your behaviors to be
consistent with the MEU principle.
And also what this theorem means is even
though you are human and you are
individual, and you have all these
subtle preferences that are nuanced
and reflect your innermost workings,
sorry, you can in fact be reduced to a
utility function.
It's just the way it is.
Unless you violate the axioms of
rationality, and hopefully you don't.